On the evening of March 10th, 2026, a family in Taiwan received a LINE message from their father.
2026年3月10日傍晚，台灣一個家庭收到了父親傳來的LINE訊息。
"I had a mountain incident. Please report for rescue." "Xi Luan Da Shan (西巒大山)."
「我發生山難，幫我通報。」「西巒大山。」
Then nothing. His phone went silent.
之後什麼都沒有了。他的手機沉默了。
This is the story of Mr. Wei (魏).
這是魏先生的故事。
A retired man. A beginner hiker.
一位退休男士。一位登山新手。
And a mountain that does not forgive mistakes.
還有一座不容犯錯的山。
Mr. Wei retired just two years ago.
魏先生兩年前剛退休。
Like many people in Taiwan, he was busy his whole life.
和許多台灣人一樣，他的一生都很忙碌。
Work. Family. Responsibilities. After retirement, he finally found time for the mountains.
工作、家庭、責任。退休後，他終於有時間走進山林。
He started hiking. He fell in love with it.
他開始爬山，並深深愛上了這件事。
At 3:35 in the morning, a security camera caught him leaving his home in Yuanlin (員林).
凌晨3點35分，員林家門口的監視器拍到他離家的身影。
He rode his scooter toward the mountains.
他騎著摩托車，朝山的方向駛去。
His destination: Xi Luan Da Mountain (西巒大山).
他的目的地：西巒大山。
One of the Taiwan Hundred Peaks (台灣百岳) — over three thousand meters high.
台灣百岳之一，海拔超過三千公尺。
This mountain does not require a permit. Anyone can enter.
這座山不需要申請入山許可，任何人都可以進入。
But the mountain does not care who you are. Every hiker must take their own responsibility.
但山不在乎你是誰，每位登山者都必須為自己的安全負責。
He told no one where he was going.
他沒有告訴任何人他要去哪裡。
When his family contacted us, I started with the usual questions.
當家屬聯繫上跑山獸時，我開始詢問一些常見的問題。
Hiking experience? He only started after retirement.
登山經驗？退休後才開始爬山。
Offline map? Probably not.
離線地圖？應該沒有。
In fact — he had gotten lost on his previous hike.
事實上，他上次爬山就曾經迷路。
Headlamp? Unlikely. He always hiked light.
頭燈？不太可能，他向來輕裝上陣。
Emergency plan? None shared with family.
緊急應變計畫？家人一無所知。
The distress message said he had an incident in the mountains.
求救訊息說他在山上發生了意外。
But it said nothing about where exactly.
但完全沒說明確切位置。
No GPS coordinates. No landmark. No distance along the trail.
沒有GPS座標、沒有地標、沒有說在步道哪個位置
Just the mountain name.
只有山的名字。
That is a very large area.
那是一片非常廣大的區域。
I had three scenarios. Injury on the main trail.
我有三種推測：在主要步道上受傷
Got lost — and got late. Or got lost — and then had an accident.
迷路後天黑或是迷路後發生意外。
The cell phone tower data would tell me more.
手機基地台的訊號資料可以告訴我更多
But I did not have it yet.
但我當時還沒取得。
And the first 72 hours matter most.
而且前72小時是最關鍵的。
I woke up after three hours of sleep. And I went to search.
我睡了三個小時後起床，出發搜尋。
On day two — 36 hours after his distress message — I arrived at the mountain.
第二天，也就是求救訊息發出後36小時，我抵達了山區。
The official search teams were working the main trail.
官方搜救隊正在搜索主要步道。
I went to look at the other options.
我則去查看其他可能的路線。
Mr. Wei had chatted with a friend the week before about this hike.
失蹤前一週，魏先生曾與朋友聊到這次登山計畫
He also mentioned the old logging village (巒安堂).
也提到了巒安堂這個舊伐木村落。
The friend told him there was another trail entry from the village side.
朋友告訴他，從村落那側也有一個登山口。
That conversation may have planted an idea —
那段對話或許在他心中種下了一個念頭。
to walk down by the forest road on the way back.
回程時走林道下山。
Since official rescue were already on the main trail, I decided to give a chance to the idea
由於官方搜救已在主要步道進行，我決定試試另一個可能
that he had lost his way on the second part of the forest road, coming from the old village side.
他是否在人倫林道後半段、靠近舊村落的林道上迷了路。
I searched along the broken second half of the forest road, toward the ruins of the old village.
我沿著殘破的林道後半段搜索，朝舊村落廢墟的方向前進。
Long. Remote. With many landslides.
路途漫長、偏遠，沿途多處崩塌。
His scooter was found parked near the gate at kilometer 17 of Renlun Forest Road (人倫林道).
他的摩托車停在人倫林道17公里處的閘門附近。
Near that gate, there is a small memorial tower.
閘門旁有一座小型紀念碑
It was built in 1961 to honour over 70 veterans who died building this road.
建於1961年，是為了紀念超過70位在修建這條道路時犧牲的榮民。
Their bones are still here, in the mountains.
他們的骸骨至今仍長眠在這片山中。
Beyond the gate, the road continues deeper. But it is no longer passable by vehicle.
越過閘門，林道繼續向山深處延伸，但已無法供車輛通行。
I walked this section myself. I passed several landslides and ruins of old working houses along the way.
我親自走過這段路，沿途經過多處崩塌和廢棄工寮的殘骸。
The effort to build this route is almost impossible to imagine today.
很難想像當年建造這條道路需要付出多大的努力。
Construction of Renlun Forest Road (人倫林道) began in 1959, under the Republic of China government.
人倫林道於1959年在中華民國政府主導下開始修建。
By 1960, a full working village had been established deep in the forest.
到了1960年，深山中已建立起一座完整的工作聚落
At kilometer 37 — at 2600 meters elevation — Luan An Tang (巒安堂).
位於37公里處、海拔2600公尺的巒安堂。
Over one hundred people lived there.
這裡曾住著超過一百人
Offices. Dormitories. A small temple. A machine room. Electricity.
並有著辦公室、宿舍、小廟、機房，甚至還有電力供應。
And below the village — a greenhouse garden.
村落下方還有一座溫室花園
The only place in Taiwan at the time where peonies were grown.
是當時台灣唯一種植牡丹的地方。
Four hundred peony trees.
四百棵牡丹樹。
The flowers were cut and sent directly to the President's wife, Soong May-ling (宋美齡).
花朵採摘後直接送往總統夫人宋美齡。
Even tourists used to come here by bus.
當年甚至有遊客搭乘巴士來到這裡。
Now you can barely walk the road safely.
而現在，這條路已幾乎無法安全通行。
The village sits at 2600 meters. The summit is only 500 meters higher.
村落海拔2600公尺，距山頂只差500公尺。
That gives you an idea of how different this mountain felt from the eastern side.
這讓你能想像，從東側進山的感受有多麼不同。
Today, all of it is ruins.
如今，一切都成了廢墟。
I saw remains of gondola cables — the lifts that once moved logs down the mountain.
我看到了纜車鋼索的殘骸，那是當年用來將木材運下山的設備。
And I saw something else.
我還看到了別的東西
A freshly cut block of wood. Clean cuts. Very recent.
一塊剛被鋸下的木頭，切口整齊，顯然是最近才發生的。
This is the work of so-called Mountain Rats (山老鼠) — people who illegally remove timber from protected forests.
這是所謂「山老鼠」的傑作——非法竊取保護林木的人。
It is prohibited now.
這是違法行為。
But it is worth remembering: the logging companies themselves cut down enormous amounts of ancient trees.
但值得記住的是，伐木公司當年砍伐了大量珍貴的古木。
The Mountain Rats are taking what little is left.
山老鼠不過是在搶奪所剩無幾的一切。
The old forest road is no longer used by hikers. All trail markers have been removed.
這條舊林道已不再供登山者使用，所有路標都已撤除。
Part of the road still serves one purpose — accessing a water source from the main river.
林道現在只剩一個用途——通往主河川的取水點。
There are actually three ways to reach Xi Luan Da Mountain (西巒大山).
抵達大西巒山其實有三條路線。
The classic hiking trail from kilometer 17 of Renlun Forest Road (人倫林道).
第一條是從人倫林道17公里處出發的經典步道
Just over six kilometers. But it climbs from 1500 meters to 3081 meters.
全長略超過六公里，但從海拔1500公尺爬升至3081公尺
One thousand six hundred meters of elevation gain. Steep. Technical.
累積爬升高達1600公尺，坡度陡峭，地形技術性高。
The second route continues along this broken second half of Renlun Forest Road (人倫林道),
第二條路線沿著人倫林道後半段的殘破道路，穿越巒安堂廢墟。
This road is too damaged even for experienced hikers.
這條路連有經驗的登山者都難以通行。
The third route comes from the north — via Shuanglong Forest Road (雙龍林道).
第三條路線從北側進入，經由雙龍林道
A longer approach, usually with a night or two spent in the old village.
行程較長，通常需要在舊村落過一至兩夜。
Some hikers call Xi Luan Da Mountain (西巒大山) "weak-knee mountain."
有些登山者稱大西巒山為「膝軟大山」。
After my first day of 27 kilometers — with 2250 meters of elevation gain
在我第一天走完27公里、爬升2250公尺的搜索路程後
of searching, I understood why.
我完全理解了這個稱號。
By now I had the cell phone tower data.
這時我已取得手機基地台的訊號資料。
After 6:18 in the evening on March 10th,
3月10日下午6點18分之後
his phone lost signal from towers in the south — in the Alishan (阿里山) area.
他的手機失去了南方阿里山一帶基地台的訊號
But it was still connecting — weakly — from Puli (埔里) and Sun Moon Lake (日月潭) area.
但仍微弱地連接著北方的埔里和日月潭地區的基地台。
And his last tower — on a peak called Jinlongshan (金龍山), which I know well from my gravel biking.
最後一個基地台位於金龍山山頂，那是我騎自行車時非常熟悉的地方。
These towers all have visibility to the north face of the mountain.
這些基地台都面向山的北側，
This told me something important. He had moved north of the main ridge.
這告訴了我一件重要的事：他已經移動到主稜線的北方。
Around the 6-kilometer mark,
在步道約6公里處
it is easy to lose the trail. It will lead you down into the creek on the north side of the mountain.
很容易迷失方向，並往北側的溪谷方向走去。
There is also something unique about this area right now.
這個區域目前還有一個特殊情況
The mountain bamboo — which normally makes off-trail movement almost impossible — had dried out completely.
原本讓人難以穿越的箭竹林已全面枯死。
When bamboo dies across a whole slope, it opens up like a corridor.
當整片坡面的竹子死去，地形就像走廊一樣開闊
You can walk almost anywhere.
幾乎可以朝任何方向行走。
That sounds like freedom. And for exploring, it is.
這聽起來像是一種自由，對於探索來說確實如此。
But it also means a lost hiker can wander very far, very fast, in completely random terrain.
但這也表示，迷路的登山客可能會在陌生地形中四處亂走迅速走遠。
No path. No reference. Just open forest — going down.
沒有路，沒有參照物，只有一片開闊的森林——而且是往下走。
I marked the creek on the north side as my hot zone. On day four, I went there.
我將北側的溪谷標記為重點搜索區域。第四天，我前往那裡。
While I search — let me tell you what I think went wrong.
在我搜索的同時，讓我告訴你我認為哪些地方出了問題。
Mr. Wei made choices that many hikers make. I am not here to blame him.
魏先生所做的選擇，許多登山者也會做出同樣的判斷。我不是要責怪他
But these lessons can save lives. Maybe even yours.
但這些教訓可以救人，也許包括你。
First — tell someone where you are going. Exact plan. Trailhead name. Expected return time.
第一：告訴別人你要去哪裡。完整的計畫、登山口名稱、預計返回時間。
His family did not even know which mountain he was on.
他的家人甚至不知道他去了哪座山。
Second — learn how to send your GPS coordinates in an emergency.
第二：學會在緊急狀況下傳送GPS座標。
It is simple. Four decimal points is enough — something like 23.7130, 120.9082.
方法很簡單，小數點後四位就夠了，例如23.7130, 120.9082。
That one message could have saved the search teams days.
這一則訊息就能為搜救隊節省好幾天的時間。
Your phone already knows exactly where you are. The problem is — nobody else does.
你的手機已經知道你在哪裡，問題是——沒有其他人知道。
Third — always carry a headlamp. A real headlamp — not your phone as a torch.
第三：一定要攜帶頭燈，真正的頭燈，而不是用手機代替。
A headlamp keeps your hands free on technical terrain. And it does not drain your phone battery.
頭燈能讓你在技術性地形上保持雙手自由，也不會消耗手機電量。
Also — your phone is your lifeline. Do not use it as a flashlight.
記住，手機是你的生命線，不要把它當手電筒用。
Fourth — bring a power bank and a charging cable.
第四：攜帶行動電源和充電線。
A dead phone is a dead connection to the world.
沒電的手機就等於與世界失去聯繫。
I once forgot my cable at home. Carried a power bank all day for nothing.
我曾經把充電線忘在家裡，帶著行動電源走了一整天卻毫無用處。
Do not be like me.
不要像我一樣。
Fifth — use an offline map.
第五：使用離線地圖。
Apps like GreenTracks (綠野遊蹤) or mapy.com work without any cell signal.
綠野遊蹤或mapy.com這類App在沒有訊號的地方也能使用。
Download the offline topo map for all of Taiwan before you go. It costs nothing. It takes five minutes.
出發前先下載全台灣的離線地形圖，免費，只需五分鐘。
Then test it on an easy hike first — before you need it.
然後先在輕鬆的路線上測試，在真正需要之前先熟悉它。
Sixth — do not go in bad weather.
第六：天氣不好就不要去爬山。山永遠都在，它會等你的。
The mountains are always there. They will wait for you.
山永遠都在，它會等你的。
And one more thing I always recommend.
還有一件我一直建議的事：
Carry a lighter. Or two, if you go overnight.
帶一個打火機，如果要過夜就帶兩個。
Not for cigarettes. Not to make fire carelessly.
不是為了抽菸，也不是隨意生火。
But in a true emergency — fire is warmth. Fire is a signal. Fire can save your life.
但在真正的緊急情況下，火是溫暖，火是求救信號，火可以救你一命。
In over 40 SAR cases I have worked — no missing hiker has ever done this.
在我處理過的40多個搜救案例中，從來沒有任何一位失蹤者這樣做過。
Please think about it.
請認真想想。
And one last thing. Do not be shy to ask for help.
最後一件事：不要不好意思求助。
Call 119 in Taiwan, or 112 — which works across all networks.
在台灣撥打119，或撥112，這個號碼跨越所有電信網路都能使用。。
Do not wait until the last moment. Do not worry about being a burden.
不要等到最後一刻，不要擔心造成別人的麻煩。
The people who answer that call — they want to help you.
接到那通電話的人，是真心想幫助你的。
Day four. Thirty-three searchers. Volunteers and professional teams.
第四天。三十三名搜救人員，包括志工和專業隊伍
The mountain divided into zones.
將山區劃分為不同的搜索區域。
I worked independently — in my hot zones along the creek below the north slope.
我獨自行動，在北側山坡下方的溪谷熱區搜索。
The creek had several smaller waterfalls, challenging even for me to climb.
溪谷中有幾處小瀑布，即使對我來說攀越也相當困難。
Along the creek — just steep walls and drops on every side.
溪道兩側盡是陡峭的岩壁和落差。
I was using the NetMonster app to compare my cell signal to his last known towers.
我用NetMonster App比對自己的手機訊號與他最後已知基地台的資料。
Deeper in the creek, the signal really matched.
越深入溪谷，訊號越吻合。
But it may just have meant I was on the north face — the area was still huge.
但這也可能只是因為我處於北面——搜索範圍依然廣大。
I searched the creek and the slopes all morning.
我整個上午都在搜索溪谷和周邊山坡
I used my drone to look under deep waterfalls and sections I could not physically reach. Nothing suspicious.
並用空拍機查看深處的瀑布底部和我無法親自抵達的地方。沒有特別的發現。
Then I decided to climb back up toward the 3.8-kilometer mark — near the old observation tower (瞭望台).
於是我決定往上攀，回到步道3.8公里處——瞭望台附近。
I met another team near the ridge. They said they had heard a whistle below.
我在稜線附近遇到另一支隊伍，他們說聽到下方有哨音。
Then I continued down alone and spotted a group below
我獨自繼續往下走，發現下方有一組人
whistling and calling out his name.
他們正吹著哨子、大聲呼叫魏先生的名字。
My heart started racing. I moved carefully through the terrain to get closer.
我的心跳開始加速。我小心翼翼地穿越地形，快步靠近。
Then a message from the family came through. These serach volunteers had found something.
這時家屬傳來訊息：搜救志工們發現了東西。
A black visor. Some snack wrappers. They belonged to Mr. Wei.
一頂黑色遮陽帽、幾個零食包裝袋，都屬於魏先生。
I joined the group. We kept going down, checking both sides of the creek.
我加入了這支隊伍，繼續往下，仔細搜查溪谷兩側。
Petr : Petr. Beast Runner.
Petr : Petr．跑山獸
Petr : But where is the hat?
Petr : 可是帽子哪裡
Searcher : You need to go down there.
搜救人員 : 你要下去下面看 Petr : 帽子哪裡
Searcher : The hat is right across from us, where that female team member is.
搜救人員 : 你要高繞到那個位置 Petr : 謝謝小姐
But then I found something. Something that brought a small hope.
就在這時，我發現了一些東西，帶來了一線希望。
An old forest road. Or rather — an old forest railway. Not recorded on any map.
搜救人員 : 帽子在你要跨過這個溪溝，到那邊那個女生位置 更確切地說，是一條舊林業鐵道，在任何地圖上都找不到記載。
This kind of track was used during the logging era to move timber down the mountain.
一條舊林道這種軌道在伐木時代用於將木材運下山。
If Mr. Wei had been wandering here — disoriented, looking for a way out — he might have found this road.
如果魏先生在這一帶茫然遊蕩、尋找出路，他有可能發現了這條路。
That gave me a little hope. He could still be alive. Even though the mountains were freezing overnight.
這給了我一點希望。他也許還活著，儘管山上的夜晚極為寒冷。
The railway led horizontally — at the same elevation — toward the river on the east.
鐵道沿著等高線水平延伸，朝東側的河流方向前進。
There were ruins of a working house. I went to the river and called out his name.
沿途有廢棄工寮的遺跡。我走到河邊，大聲呼喊他的名字。
Petr: Anyone there?
Petr : 有人嗎？
No answer.
沒有回應。
I went back to the group.
我回到了隊伍中。
Meanwhile, two brave searchers(彰化特搜) had set ropes at the end of the creek
與此同時，兩位勇敢的搜救人員(彰化特搜)在溪谷末端架好繩索
and rappelled over the edge to look down.
垂降到邊緣下方查看。
There — at the narrow base of a twenty-meter waterfall — they spotted Mr. Wei.
就在那裡——在一道二十公尺高瀑布的狹窄底部——他們看到了魏先生。
He had not survived.
他已經不在了。
The wall under the waterfall is over one hundred meters high.
瀑布下方的岩壁高達一百多公尺
He fell twenty meters — onto the first ledge.
他墜落了二十公尺，落在第一個岩階上
Located two hundred fifty meters below the ridge with the main trail.
位於主步道稜線以下約兩百五十公尺處。
The next day, the professional rescue teams used a SKED and ropes to lift him to the top of the waterfall.
隔天，專業搜救隊使用SKED擔架和繩索，將他吊升至瀑布頂端，
Then a helicopter brought him the rest of the way down.
再由直升機接力，將他送下山。
He came home. Back to his family.
他回家了，回到了家人身邊。
So what happened?
究竟發生了什麼事？
He most likely got lost near the 3.8-kilometer mark.
他最可能是在步道3.8公里處附近迷路。
There is a relatively flat, open forested area near the old observation tower (瞭望台).
瞭望台旁有一片相對平坦開闊的林地。
It was getting dark. He had no headlamp. No light at all.
當時天色漸暗，他沒有頭燈，完全沒有任何光源。
After the examination, it appears he may have tried to call for help
根據事後的檢查，他似乎曾嘗試求救
but the signal was poor.
但訊號太差。
If you are ever in serious trouble in the mountains — call 119 in Taiwan, or 112.
如果你在山上遇到嚴重困難，請撥打台灣的119，或112。
He kept going downhill. That is the instinct — find a way out.
他繼續往下走。那是一種本能——找到出路。
But that is always wrong.
但這樣做永遠是錯的。
On terrain like this, going downhill randomly almost always leads to a waterfall. Or a cliff.
在這樣的地形中，隨意往下走幾乎一定會遇到瀑布或懸崖。
There is no safe way down except the trail you came from.
除了原路返回，沒有安全的下山方式。
His phone was found in the zipped pocket of his jacket. His bag still had food in it.
他的手機被發現放在外套的拉鍊口袋裡，背包裡還有食物。
The fall was fatal. And it happened that first night.
墜落是致命的，而且就發生在第一個夜晚。
This mountain is beautiful.
這是一座美麗的山。
People come here for a day hike to the summit. Or for two days — spending a night in the ruins of the old village.
有人來這裡當天來回攻頂，有人選擇兩天行程，在舊村落廢墟中過夜。
I understand why people come here.
我理解為什麼人們會來這裡。
But the mountains do not care how fit you are, how early you started, or how determined you feel.
但山不在乎你體能多好、出發多早，或你有多大的決心。
You have to take responsibility. You have to prepare well.
你必須為自己負責，你必須做好充分準備。
And sometimes — you have to give up. Turn back. Cancel the trip.
而且有時候，你必須放棄——折返、取消行程。
That decision is not failure. That decision is wisdom.
那個決定不是失敗，那個決定是智慧。
Mr. Wei loved hiking.
魏先生熱愛登山。
He found something in these mountains after a lifetime of work.
他在辛苦工作一輩子後，在這片山林中找到了某種珍貴的東西。
I respect that deeply.
我深深尊重這一點。
I hope his story helps the next hiker come home safely.
我希望他的故事能幫助下一位登山者平安回家。
The mountains will always be there. Be ready when you go.
山永遠都在。出發前，請做好準備。